<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE knimeNode PUBLIC "-//UNIKN//DTD KNIME Node 2.0//EN" "http://www.knime.org/Node.dtd">
<knimeNode type="Source" icon="./xmlread.png" deprecated="true">
    <name>XML Reader</name>
    <shortDescription>Reads a XML File.</shortDescription>
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
            Reads a well formed XML document. An XPath query can be specified to 
            read only a portion of the file. In this case the output will be
            the nodes in the document that match the XPath query.
		</intro>
        <option name="Selected File">
            The XML document to read. It can be a local file on disk or a URL.
        </option>
        <option name="Use XPath Filter">
            If checked, only the nodes of the document, which match den XPath 
            query, will be read.
        </option>
        <option name="XPath Query">
            <p>Only nodes of the document, which match this XPath query, will be 
            read. Each matching node is read in a single data cell.</p>
            
            <p>Note, that XPath requires to explicitly denote namespaces. E.g. to
            read only the body of a XHTML document you can use the XPath query:
            <br/>
            <i>/dns:html/dns:body</i>
            <br/>
            where dns is the prefix of the namespace defined in the 
            <b>Namespaces</b> table.</p>
            
            <p>A limited XPath syntax is supported. Only absolute paths to
            nodes can be defined. Among the XPath operators the |-Operator
            is supported. It can be used to read e.g. the head and the body of 
            an XHTML document in single cells:
            <br/>
            <i>/dns:html/dns:head | /dns:html/dns:body</i> </p>
        </option>
        <option name="Namespaces">
            The prefixes and the namespaces used in the XPath query. For the
            example in <b>XPath Query</b> following namespace must be defined:
            <br/>
            Prefix: <i>pre</i>
            <br/>
            Namespace: <i>http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml</i>         
        </option>
        <option name="Incorporate namespace of the root element.">
            <p>This option is useful when you do not have the default
            namespace of your document at hand.</p>
        	<p>If checked, the namespace of the root element is added to the 
        	<b>Namespaces</b> table during runtime. Please define a prefix for this 
        	namespace in <b>Prefix of root's namespace</b>.</p>
        	<p>For the example of XHTML documents the namespace of the root 
        	element is http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml so that with the
        	root's prefix of <i>dns</i> you can leave
        	the <b>Namespaces</b> table empty.</p>     
        </option>        
    </fullDescription>

    <ports>
        <outPort name="Read table" index="0">
            The complete XML document in a single data cell or the nodes
            matching the XPath query if XPath filtering is checked.
        </outPort>
    </ports>
</knimeNode>


